<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="en-UK">
  <title>Maximvdw&#39;s Blog</title>
  <subtitle>An open-source hybrid positioning system framework.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://maximvdw.be/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://maximvdw.be"/>
  <updated>2024-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://maximvdw.be</id>
  <author>
    <name>Maxim Van de Wynckel</name>
    <email>maxim.van.de.wynckel@vub.be</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>FOSDEM 2025: Discovering indoor environments and positioning systems</title>
    <link href="https://maximvdw.be/posts/2024/12/18/"/>
    <updated>2024-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://maximvdw.be/posts/2024/12/18/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever gotten lost in a building and wished they had some sort of navigation system or at least a floor plan? I have, unfortunately, and it was only later that I realised that not only they had a floor plan online - but they had a navigation app for that building. The reality is that a user who is not familiar with a building will not find such an app until it&#39;s too late. Indoor environments sometimes have public floorplans available via some service. Similarly, more and more indoor positioning systems are being deployed in buildings to provide navigation services or asset tracking. However, as a person visiting a building, you are often not aware that these services exist or where to find them. Even if some global registry exists to discover this data, it is often proprietary, discouraging developers from interfacing with such systems. I want to bring a shift into the landscape of indoor positioning systems and services and solve this! In this presentation, I will talk about discovering indoor environments and positioning systems through local and global discovery methods, linked data and personal data vaults. How nice would it be, that instead of downloading the FOSDEM app, you simply use Google Maps or any open-source navigation application to find the location of this talk?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>